<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd on the 30th of January vindicating King Charles the Martyr, and the keeping of the day by E.H. ; which may serve for an answer to Mr. Stephen's sermon preach'd on the 30th of January, before the honourable House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18112518</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18112518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1124:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd on the 30th of January vindicating King Charles the Martyr, and the keeping of the day by E.H. ; which may serve for an answer to Mr. Stephen's sermon preach'd on the 30th of January, before the honourable House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are sold by J. Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stephens, William, d. 1718. --  Sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, January 30, 1699/1700.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 1st, XXI, 12-13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106837:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd on the 30th of <hi>January:</hi> VINDICATING King <hi>CHARLES</hi> THE MARTYR, AND THE <hi>Keeping of the Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>E. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which may ſerve for an ANSWER To Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s SERMON, Preach'd on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> before the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, and are Sold by <hi>I. Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:106837:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106837:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd on the 30th of <hi>January, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Kings XXI. 12, 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>They Proclaimed a Faſt, and ſet <hi>Naboth</hi> on high among the People.</p>
                  <p>And there came in two Men, Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> and ſat before him, and the Men of <hi>Belial</hi> witneſſed againſt him, even againſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the People, ſaying, <hi>Naboth</hi> did Blaſpheme God and the King. Then they carried him forth out of the City, and Stoned him with Stones, that he Dyed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ERE's a ſad <hi>Story</hi> in the Text, to bring to our Remembrance <hi>this day</hi> a more Tragical and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan'd Hiſtory of a <hi>Later</hi> Date.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Blood-ſhed</hi> in the Text, and <hi>That</hi> of this ſad occaſion, are too much <hi>Parallel: Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard made him the only Blaſphemer of his City, and fit to die; he muſt forfeit his <hi>Life,</hi> that he may forfeit his <hi>Lands:</hi> And the glorious <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> of this daies <hi>Celebration</hi> muſt forfeit His <hi>Head,</hi> that He might forfeit the <hi>Diadem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both of them therefore were thought <hi>worthy</hi> to Die, becauſe <hi>worth</hi> the Killing. The greateſt Purſe is the beloved Prey of the greateſt Thieves. The <hi>ſtatelieſt</hi> Cedar muſt firſt feel the <hi>Ax:</hi> And the Tree with the goodlieſt, and <hi>beſt grown</hi> Branches, muſt be ſooneſt <hi>Lopt.</hi> Thus ourbeſt <hi>Deer</hi> muſt be firſt <hi>Deſtroy'd.</hi> And <hi>both</hi> fall by the hands of <hi>men of Belial:</hi> And yet, <hi>Both,</hi> with the ſpecious and plauſible Formalities of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Religion. <hi>They proclaimed a Faſt,</hi> ſought the Lord, Faſted and Wept; as if their <hi>Tender Conſciences</hi> durſt attempt nothing without <hi>Advice</hi> firſt from the <hi>Oracle</hi> of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106837:3"/> 2. Juſtice. <hi>They ſet up a Court of Judicature;</hi> and firſt <hi>ſet</hi> Naboth <hi>on high among the People,</hi> and then bring in their <hi>Evidence, two Men, Children of</hi> Belial, Knights of the <hi>Poſt,</hi> (as the like wretches did againſt our <hi>Saviour</hi> and our <hi>Sovereign) This Man Blaſphemed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Impudent <hi>Cruelty!</hi> Is not <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Murder</hi> ſufficiently Solemn without the <hi>mockery</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Juſtice?</hi> Is it not enough to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flower</hi> Innocence, but muſt <hi>Religion</hi> be the <hi>Pander?</hi> Is't not enough to <hi>Enſnare</hi> the Righteous, but muſt <hi>Divinity</hi> be the <hi>Stalking-Horſe?</hi> Muſt the Fountain of <hi>Light</hi> be brought in as an <hi>Acceſſary</hi> to the works of <hi>Darkneſs?</hi> Is not the Devil <hi>Fiend</hi> enough, except he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Light?</hi> And is nothing but the Glorious <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> a fit <hi>Mask</hi> for ſuch <hi>Loathſome Deformities?</hi> Is this <hi>Religion?</hi> Is this the <hi>Cauſe?</hi> My <hi>Letany</hi> muſt be that of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s, in Deteſtation of his <hi>Bloody</hi> Sons, thoſe Inſtruments of Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Oh my Soul, come not into their Secrets; unto their Aſſembly, mine Honour, be not thou united,</hi> Gen. 49.6.</p>
            <p>A doleful <hi>Tragedy</hi> then is the <hi>Text;</hi> which begins <hi>Speciouſly,</hi> but ends in <hi>Heavineſs;</hi> begins <hi>Gorgeouſly,</hi> but ends in <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when I read the <hi>firſt</hi> words, <hi>They proclaimed a Faſt,</hi> my ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized Meditations can ſcarcely <hi>credit</hi> my Eyes, when they view the <hi>laſt</hi> words, <hi>They ſtoned him with ſtones;</hi> ſo incongruous is the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Who can imagine that <hi>Murder</hi> ſhould <hi>ſtain</hi> the <hi>Epilogue,</hi> when the <hi>Prologue</hi> was ſo gloriouſly <hi>gilded</hi> with <hi>Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>words</hi> then are nothing elſe, but the deſcription of a <hi>High Court of Juſtice,</hi> ſolemnly Erected by Wicked Men, <hi>Men of Belial,</hi> Celebrated with the <hi>eſpecious</hi> Pretext of a <hi>Religious Faſt,</hi> to <hi>avouch</hi> the Arraignment, and Bloody <hi>Sentence</hi> paſt upon a Guiltleſs Man: Veiling the <hi>Murder</hi> with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage</hi> of <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and therefore publickly <hi>Solomnized</hi> in the preſence of the <hi>People;</hi> not <hi>Covertly,</hi> as <hi>Richard</hi> the Third Murder'd his Nephews; but <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,</hi> and before the Sun.</p>
            <p>Wherein Six <hi>Particulars</hi> do eſpecially preſent themſelves to our Conſideration; all too ſutable (if it had been the will of GOD to the contrary) to the <hi>Bewailed</hi> Occaſion of this dayes Remembrance: The <hi>Laſt</hi> whereof ought, in our Method, to be <hi>Firſt</hi> taken notice of.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>What was done: A Bloody Murder,</hi> They Stoned.</item>
               <item>II. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon whom it was done: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon an Innocent Man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>By whom it was done: By</hi> Men of <hi>Belial.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106837:3"/>
               <item> IV. <hi>Before whom it was done:</hi> In the preſence of the People.</item>
               <item>V. <hi>How it was done: With the Method and Formalities of</hi> Piety <hi>and</hi> Juſtice.</item>
               <item>VI. <hi>Why it was done: The pretended cauſe was,</hi> his Blaſphemy: <hi>But,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The true Cauſe is expreſt in the ſixth and ſeventh Verſes of this Chapter. <hi>Ahab</hi> Longed for the pleaſant Vineyard, and <hi>Jezabel</hi> will ſtay the Longing of this greedy <hi>Cannibal,</hi> tho' it be with <hi>Mans Fleſh;</hi> and quench his covetous Thirſt with a <hi>Draught</hi> of <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Naboth</hi> had been Poor and Lean, he had eſcap'd amongſt the <hi>Raſcal</hi> Herd; but he was too Fat and Fair-like, to avoid the <hi>Shambles</hi> of theſe bloody Butchers. His fertile Field, like another <hi>Golgotha,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Price</hi> of <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Pleaſant <hi>Vineyards,</hi> the Tempting <hi>Crown-Lands,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops-Lands,</hi> expos'd the Sacred Perſon of our Sovereign to the rapacious Jaws of our keener <hi>Wolves.</hi> Our <hi>Loftieſt</hi> Mountains were moſt <hi>ſubject</hi> to the Storm.</p>
            <p>The Text will furniſh us with Three <hi>Obſervations,</hi> ſeaſonable for our Meditations this day. I will ſpeak to each of them, as far as may ſute with the preſent occaſion, which yet will afford us a large field of Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Many times in this Life the Worſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage does befal the Beſt of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's no juſt offence given, yet <hi>Naboth</hi> muſt die the death of a Murtherer.</p>
            <p>Innocence, we ſee, is no ſure Protection; nay, 'tis ſometimes <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign'd,</hi> when Villany goes <hi>ſcot-free,</hi> or (it may be) ſits on the <hi>Bench;</hi> as if <hi>Aſtraea</hi>'s flight was no Poetical fiction, but a real Hiſtory; as if there was no Reward for the Righteous, nor a GOD that judgeth in the Earth.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Hemlock</hi> and the worſt of <hi>Weeds</hi> may out-live a Storm, when the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Lilly</hi> is Deflowred. <hi>Manaſſeth,</hi> that <hi>Monſter</hi> of Men, Reign'd the longeſt of any of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> yet good <hi>Joſiah</hi> was ſlain in Battel; and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> lived to ſee Three Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many <hi>Brutes</hi> out-live Men; and many <hi>brutiſh</hi> men the <hi>beſt</hi> of men. Sure I am, our worſt <hi>Ivies</hi> flouriſhed, when the Royal <hi>Oak,</hi> that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported them, was dead.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay to theſe things? This ſtrange and uncouth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106837:4"/>viſage of Providence did ſo ſtartle the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> that it almoſt frighted him out of his <hi>Faith:</hi> He knew not what to think on't, but was ready to ſay, <hi>Verily I have cleanſed my Heart in vain, and waſhed my Hands in Innocency: Becauſe the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly proſpered in the world. Nabal</hi> in <hi>Plenty,</hi> when <hi>David</hi> was ready to <hi>Starve</hi> for want of Bread.</p>
            <p>The chief Argument that <hi>Cicero</hi> produces to prove, That the <hi>Jews</hi> were not the People of GOD, is taken from no other <hi>Topick,</hi> then St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (who wrote not long after him) makes uſe of to the ſame <hi>Hebrews,</hi> to prove the contrary; to wit, Their frequent Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. <hi>Whom the Lord loveth, He chaſteneth, and ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every Son, whom He receiveth. If ye endure chaſtening, GOD dealeth with you, as with Sons: For what Son is be, whom the Father chaſteneth not? But if ye be without chaſtiſement, whereof all</hi> (GOD's Children) <hi>are Partakers, then are ye Baſtards, and not Sons:</hi> Whereas <hi>Tully</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids the <hi>Hebrews</hi> with their often Captivity: <hi>You may know by their Miſeries,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>how well GOD loves them.</hi> Which, however Ironi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally by him ſpoken, is undoubtedly a great <hi>Truth;</hi> I am ſure, God ſaies ſo, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. <hi>You only have I known of all the Families of the Earth, therefore will I Puniſh you.</hi> And again, threatning to <hi>throw</hi> them off, He tells them, He will <hi>throw away</hi> the Rod, and trouble Himſelf no more with them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>I will not puniſh your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when they commit Whoredom; nor your Spouſes, when they commit Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Muſcovitiſh</hi> Women are jealous, that their Husbands do not love them, if they do not beat them a little now and then. I am ſure, we may well be Jealous that GOD loves us not, if He never beats us. So <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whom I love, I rebuke, and chaſten. Succeſs</hi> therefore and <hi>Proſperity</hi> are no infallible <hi>marks</hi> of GOD's <hi>Favour</hi> to a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or <hi>People;</hi> if it were, we muſt Renounce our Saviour, Apoſtatize from Chriſtianity, and turn <hi>Renegadoes</hi> to <hi>Mahometiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis with a true <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as with a <hi>Porter;</hi> the more he <hi>bears,</hi> and the oftener he is <hi>burthened,</hi> the more is his <hi>benefit</hi> tho' the <hi>load</hi> be heavy. St. <hi>Peter</hi> therefore, who had his <hi>Back-burthen</hi> of Afflictions, eſteem'd a <hi>tempted</hi> and <hi>tryed Faith,</hi> as <hi>tryed Gold;</hi> the <hi>hotter</hi> the <hi>Fire,</hi> the <hi>purer</hi> will be the <hi>Metal:</hi> The more <hi>fiery</hi> a Believers Tryal, the more <hi>ſplendid</hi> will be his Graces.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ruſtick</hi> anſwered <hi>Luther</hi> as Profanely as Clowniſhly, when the good <hi>Father</hi> told him in the extremity of his Sickneſs, That ſuch Chaſtiſements were Gods <hi>Love-tokens: Then</hi> (anſwered he) <hi>let Him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106837:4"/>keep them to Himſelf for me, or give them to His beſt friends.</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Beza</hi> made a better uſe of his Sickneſs at <hi>Paris,</hi> which he calls "The cauſe of his Health, <hi>Morbus iſle ſanitatis meae principium:</hi> That Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſaith he, made me Well.</p>
            <p>'Tis often beſt with the Soul, when 'tis worſt with the Body: <hi>Wounds</hi> in the Fleſh may prove <hi>Vulneratives</hi> to the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Corrections</hi> prove <hi>Inſtructions:</hi> We have the Wiſe Man's word to avouch it; and he might ſpeak Experimentally; for his Proſperity did him more harm, than all his Wiſdom did him good, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Reproofs of Inſtruction are the way of Life.</hi> Heb. <hi>The Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of Inſtructions are the way of Life:</hi> For <hi>ſchola Crucis eſt ſchola Lucis;</hi> and Adverſity the beſt Univerſity.</p>
            <p>For two <hi>Reaſons</hi> therefore, (to name no more) The Beſt of Men may meet with the Worſt of Uſage in this Life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe their <hi>Portion</hi> is not here to be <hi>Paid.</hi> For tho' many times a good <hi>Joſeph</hi> enjoyes eighty eight Years of Peace and Plenty for his thirteen Years Impriſonment: Yet theſe Rewards of a Child of Gods <hi>good ſervice,</hi> are over-plus, and more than <hi>Chriſt</hi> has obliged Himſelf unto, in His laſt Will and Teſtament; <hi>In the World ye ſhall have Tribulation,</hi> that's your <hi>lot</hi> here, ſaith <hi>Chriſt; but in Me ye ſhall have Peace,</hi> that's your <hi>Portion. Omnis Chriſtianus Crucianus,</hi> Every good Chriſtian muſt wear a <hi>Crucifix. Eccleſia eſt Haeres Crucis:</hi> The Church can claim Adminiſtration of nothing in this World, but Chriſt's Croſs: Therefore it was that <hi>Ignatius,</hi> when he came to Encounter the wild Beaſts at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Now I begin to be a Chriſtian.</hi> And <hi>Luther</hi> excellently (according to his Paſſionate way) expreſſes himſelf to this purpoſe, <hi>I proteſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>GOD ſhall not put me off with a Portion in this Life. David</hi> makes it the definition of a Wicked Man, to have his Portion in this World.</p>
            <p>Why then Repineſt thou, O my Soul! that the Ungodly Proſper in the world, and dip their Polluted Hands in the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent?</hi> Why art thou caſt down, O my Soul, and why art thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me, when the <hi>Rod</hi> of the <hi>Wicked</hi> doth reſt on the <hi>Back</hi> of the <hi>Righteous?</hi> Art thou ſo Covetous that nothing will Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thee but Two Heavens! Wicked Men make a ſhift to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with their momentany Deluſions, their <hi>Bird in Hand,</hi> their flit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pleaſures! that yet take themſelves Wings and fly away! And art not thou Contented with the Permanent Incomes of God, and Chriſt, and Heaven? Sure thou art not content to change thy Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106837:5"/>(for ſuch <hi>brittle</hi> Ware as the World affords) why then not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with thy Portion? Greedy <hi>Miſer!</hi> thou wouldſt have all, and yet canſt Enjoy nothing. 'Tis ſo: Well then, good God, continue me thy Peace, and Food and Rayment, and then I will not Envy <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Beſt of Men have need of ſuch hard uſage, to bring their Sins to remembrance; to rub off the contracted ruſt, they muſt be ſometimes Scoured. <hi>David,</hi> about to be Expell'd from his Kingdoms, gave a better anſwer to Curſing <hi>Shimei;</hi> then at his Return, to Good <hi>Mephiboſheth.</hi> To be a Captive, makes man pitiful to Captives: <hi>Iſraels</hi> Bondage ſhould make them liberal to Bondmen, whereas Liberty and Fulneſs breeds Forgetfulneſs; and therefore God will Exerciſe his People with a <hi>Paroxiſme,</hi> a fit or two of diſtreſs, to be their Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers. The beſt Clothes had need ſome times to be Shaken, or they will be Duſty.</p>
            <p>Leſſons ſet on with a Whipping, are beſt remembred; and God never Whips his Children, but when no <hi>ſaying</hi> will ſerve. <hi>Ictus piſcator ſapit;</hi> even good Men, like the <hi>Wallnut-Tree,</hi> will not be <hi>fruitful,</hi> except ſometimes <hi>beaten.</hi> Good <hi>David</hi> grew almoſt <hi>wild</hi> for want of <hi>pruning.</hi> Pſal. 119.67. <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray, but now have I kept thy word.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But to Apply this to the preſent Occaſion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. This may ſerve to ſtate our Judgments aright in the conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Croſs Providences.</p>
               <p>I call them <hi>Croſs</hi>-Providences, not that any Providence can poſſibly be really croſs or adverſe, either to a Child of God, or Gods Glory, (who alwayes makes even and ſmooth work in concluſion, tho' he may ſeem to work with a <hi>crooked</hi> Tool) but becauſe it may ſeem croſs to us, thro' our ſhort and dim-ſightedneſs; or becauſe they are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to us by a falſe Medium, as a Stick half in the water, that ſeems crooked, but is not really ſo; and that you will know, if you either thruſt all the Stick into the water, or pull it out: So when Men ſee Gods Diſpenſations but by halves, they think them <hi>croſs</hi> and crooked, tho' they are not really ſo, and that they will find in the iſſue. What was more likely to croſs <hi>Joſeph</hi> in his promiſed Advancement, than to be Sold for a <hi>Bond-Slave?</hi> Yet that prov'd the fitteſt and readieſt means thereto. Thus the Wheels of Providence, like the Wheels of a Clock, may move counter, yet each Motion concur to make it go the better.</p>
               <p>Let us not therefore charge God fooliſhly, when he permits a <hi>Slave</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106837:5"/>to laſh his <hi>Children.</hi> He looks on, and will either <hi>end</hi> our ſufferings, or <hi>mend</hi> us by ſuffering. He is no loſer that <hi>loſes</hi> a Crown ſtuft with Cares, who is thereby fitted for a <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Condemn not then a <hi>Saint,</hi> becauſe God ſuffers him to be a <hi>Martyr. Chriſt</hi> himſelf was Crucified, and hanſell'd the <hi>Croſs</hi> as well as the <hi>Crown;</hi> a Crown of <hi>Thorns,</hi> as well as a Crown of <hi>Immortality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall we give <hi>Judas</hi> the <hi>ſupremacy</hi> amongſt the Apoſtles, becauſe he carried the <hi>Bagg?</hi> or <hi>enſhrine</hi> our Bloody <hi>Varlets becauſe they got the Bagg?</hi> or <hi>Chriſten</hi> Villany, Murder, and Rapin, becauſe (like Weeds) they <hi>throve</hi> and proſpered, when our wholeſomeſt Herbs were <hi>nipt</hi> in the <hi>Bud?</hi> This would be to <hi>Idolize</hi> (like the Ruder <hi>Iſraelites</hi>) a <hi>Calf,</hi> becauſe made up of <hi>Golden Ear-Rings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proſperity therefore can never <hi>avouch</hi> Impiety, nor the moſt <hi>fiery</hi> Tryal <hi>brand</hi> the Innocent. 'Twas but Tyrannous <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> tho' they Murder'd the <hi>Heir,</hi> that they might <hi>Heir</hi> his Eſtate: Haſt thou <hi>Killed,</hi> and alſo taken <hi>poſſeſſion?</hi> Is this <hi>Title</hi> good in <hi>Law?</hi> In Gods Law?</p>
               <p>Tho' Impious Men, in their fulneſs and jollity, may be moſt <hi>mad</hi> upon their villany, like Lunaticks, when the Moon's at Full, yet is this a Teſtimonial that their Heads are <hi>Light.</hi> Much Succeſs like much Wine, does but the more <hi>Intoxicate.</hi> 
                  <q>Proſperous Gales oft fill the Sails of Pirates, but does not juſtifie their <hi>Piracy,</hi> was the Expreſſion of the Royal Martyr.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This may likewiſe inform us, That if the <hi>Beſt</hi> of Men may meet with the <hi>Worſt</hi> of Uſage in this Life, then the <hi>Beſt</hi> things in this Life, are not the <hi>Beſt</hi> things. If the richeſt <hi>Liveries</hi> were the beſt <hi>Love-Tokens</hi> our Heavenly Father could give his Children, the <hi>Slave</hi> ſhould <hi>Out-brave</hi> the Son. Thoſe that have turn'd Judgement into <hi>Gall,</hi> and Righteouſneſs into <hi>Hemlock,</hi> may rejoyce in a thing of <hi>Nought:</hi> So is Proſperity termed, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.13. And ſo are thoſe <hi>Naughty</hi> Men termed in the Verſe foregoing, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.12.</p>
               <p>Men of little <hi>Worth</hi> then may have the <hi>Greateſt</hi> outward Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but thoſe are, at <hi>Beſt,</hi> Enjoyments of little worth. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Garter</hi> cannot cure the <hi>Gout,</hi> nor a Crown the Head-ach; nor a Sound <hi>Eſtate</hi> a Wounded <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Even Crowns (we ſee this day by woful Experience) have their Croſſes.</p>
               <p>Therefore it was that <hi>Antigonus</hi> call'd his <hi>Diadem,</hi> (and did not miſcal it) <hi>Vilem Pannum,</hi> an unhappy Rag, and he did not <hi>Nick-name</hi> it. And excellently well did a Noble Monarch expreſs the ſentiments
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106837:6"/>he had of his Crown, when he ſaid, <hi>He that knows the Cares with which a Crown is Stuft, wou'd hardly ſtoop to take it off the Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Chair</hi> of State cannot eaſe the <hi>Collick,</hi> nor the choiceſt <hi>Dainties</hi> the <hi>Tooth-ach:</hi> And therefore <hi>Thrones</hi> upon earth are but <hi>Bona Scabelli,</hi> God's Foot-ſtool-gifts. He reſerves the <hi>Bona Throni</hi> for his deſerving <hi>Ones:</hi> The greateſt <hi>Beauties</hi> have not always the greateſt <hi>Dowries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hiſtory tells us that a <hi>Good</hi> Man being troubled that <hi>Phocas</hi> the Traitor reigned at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and earneſt in Prayer to God to know the reaſon of it, had this anſwer, <hi>Becauſe a worſe Man could not be found:</hi> Which might have ſerved for a good Anſwer to us, when the ſame <hi>Riddle</hi> of God's ſtrange dealings puzled us in the Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Uſurpations we Lament this Day. Worſe Men, nor more Bloody Men, nor Impudent Juglers (who <hi>Tipt</hi> their Tongues with the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> when their Hands were <hi>Dipt</hi> in <hi>Blood</hi>) more abominable <hi>Varlets</hi> could not be found. Why did God <hi>Whip</hi> his choiceſt Children with <hi>Rods</hi> of Iron? The anſwer's plain: Thoſe Rods of <hi>Iron</hi> were the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Inſtruments</hi> for him to uſe in that <hi>Iron</hi> Age of harder Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but ſtill they were but Rods of <hi>Iron,</hi> though <hi>Enveloped</hi> thro' Uſurpation with Crowns of <hi>Gold:</hi> Bryars of the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> are the fitteſt to make a <hi>Scratch,</hi> and the <hi>Worſt</hi> of Men moſt apt for the <hi>Worſt</hi> of Works.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is that Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> well define; Proſperity to be <hi>Miſericordiam omnis indignatione crudeliorem,</hi> a moſt Unmerciful Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Such excellent <hi>Baubles</hi> as the Children of this World do <hi>Fancy,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given many times to the worſt of Men, as Quai<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> not to <hi>Feed</hi> but <hi>Choak</hi> them. Who would long for a fine <hi>Suit,</hi> that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the <hi>Plague?</hi> Such <hi>Infection</hi> attends all outward Mercies, if <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanſed,</hi> if <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſanctified;</hi> and therefore they are not the <hi>Beſt</hi> things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence let us ſee the <hi>Inconſtancies</hi> and <hi>Vanity</hi> of all <hi>Humane</hi> Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: As in the Text, <hi>Naboth</hi> in the Morning happy, even to the Envy of a King; and preſently after us'd like a Murderer, and from <hi>Being ſet on high amongſt the People, is forthwith pull'd down, hurried away, and Stoned to Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt Vertical heights under Heaven are the moſt Vertiginous; do but dizzy the Brains the more, and ſubject us to a Fall. There's nothing therefore ſo ſure, as that there's nothing ſure in this World: Not Crowns nor Scepters, as this days woful Advertiſement can remind us.</p>
               <p>Place not your Confidence then in any ſublunary Enjoyments, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106837:6"/>are all as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconſtant</hi> as the <hi>Moon,</hi> ſeldom looking with <hi>One</hi> and the ſame <hi>Face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let him that ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> have known what Famine is, and yet they have Boaſted, that they Enjoyed a piece of <hi>Earth</hi> that ſtood not in need of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet this glorious <hi>Birthright,</hi> for all their <hi>Vaunting,</hi> they were glad to ſell in <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s time for a <hi>Morſel</hi> of Bread (as their <hi>Grandſire Eſau</hi> did his, for a <hi>Meſs</hi> of Pottage.) So certain it is, that God will make even <hi>Atheiſts</hi> confeſs that there is nothing certain on this ſide <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which our bleſſed Martyr had a Heavenly Senſe in thoſe Pathetick and Sacred Soliloquies: <q>I thank God my Proſperity made me not wholly a Stranger to the Contemplations of Mortality; Death being an Eclipſe which oft happeneth as well in clear as cloudy days.</q> Corn upon the Houſe Top is the higheſt, but not the moſt laſting.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us take in <hi>Good</hi> part the <hi>Worſt</hi> that can befal us. <hi>Ye have not yet reſiſted unto Blood,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; intimating that ſince bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Men then they, (the Worlds <hi>Worthies,</hi> of whom the World was not <hi>Worthy</hi>) had reſiſted unto Blood, they had no reaſon to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, eſpecially ſince no Temptation had befallen them, but what was common to Men: And upon ſerious Thoughts, how can we have a diſpleaſing Thought under the harſheſt Preſſures, if we conſider that both our Saviour and our Sovereign was Buffeted, Spit upon, falſly Accuſed, and Slain.</p>
               <p>Of ſuch Uſes as theſe, the Children of God have frequent uſe, in the whole courſe of their Lives; either thro' Gods diſmaying diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards themſelves, or their Brethren. <hi>Moſes</hi> hopes were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to flag, and diſpond, when notwithſtanding Gods promiſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, their Bondage was Increaſed, and their Load the Heavier; inſomuch as <hi>Moſes,</hi> as meek as he was, Mutinouſly ſeems to Article againſt God, for breach of Promiſe, and <hi>Challenge</hi> him for the Evil Treatment that <hi>Pharab</hi> gave them. <hi>Wherefore haſt thou ſo evil Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this People? Why is it thou haſt ſent me? For ſince I came to</hi> Pharaoh <hi>to ſpeak in they Name, he hath done evil to this People; neither haſt thou delivered thy People at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe diſmal Appearances have Scared ſome into <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> though with as pitiful pretexts of reaſon, as that of <hi>Diagoras;</hi> who, becauſe a <hi>Plagiary</hi> ſtole one of his Poems, and Publiſhed it in his own Name, fell out with Providence for ſeeming to connive at the Felony, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding a <hi>Thunderbolt; and ſo bid Defiance</hi> to Heaven, and turn'd <hi>Atheiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106837:7"/>
               <p> But, <hi>Becauſe Sentence againſt wicked Men is not executed ſpeedily, ſhall the Hearts therefore of the Sons of Men be fully ſet in them to do Evil?</hi> No, certainly; there's no ſolid reaſon for it; for as Gods <hi>Forbearance</hi> is no <hi>Acquittance,</hi> ſo upon an impartial Inquiry we ſhall find that he little conſults with rational Principles, who ſuffers his <hi>Paſſion</hi> in ſiniſter diſpenſations to out-run his <hi>Prudence,</hi> or his <hi>Fears</hi> to cut-ſtrip his <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s twenty two Books <hi>De civitate De,</hi> were purpoſely writ in <hi>Vindication</hi> of <hi>Providence permitting</hi> (as here in the Text, and in the ſorrowful inſtance of this day) <hi>The Rod of the Wicked to reſt upon the Backs of the Righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Opera Dei ſunt in medijs contrarijs,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> well obſerves, God brings about his own deſigns (of Glory to himſelf, and Good to his people) by ſeemingly contrary means. Who would have thought that <hi>David</hi> ſhould have liv'd to be a King, (as God had Promiſed) that had ſeen the Stripling ready to be devoured by the Monſtrous Giant? yet that was the firſt Step (as Providence order'd it) by which he afterwards did Climb into the Throne.</p>
               <p>Of this <hi>Harmony</hi> of Providences (though they may ſeem to <hi>Jarre) Plato</hi> had a grateful Sence, when he ſaid, God did always proportion all things according to the exactneſs and order of Geometrical Rules.</p>
               <p>God does all things regularly, in Weight and Meaſure, Mood and Figure. The <hi>Grecians</hi> therefore call the World <hi>Coſmos,</hi> a Beauty, from its Lovely Order, viſible in the graceful Airs, and becoming Glances and Appearances of Providence, in the Creation, Guidance, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance of the World.</p>
               <p>Therefore if ſome of the Draughts of Providence ſeem crooked and irregular (to which unhallowed thoughts this bewailed occaſion might tempt us) yet ſuſpend your Cenſures, till the <hi>Picture</hi> be <hi>finiſhed,</hi> and then you'll ſee that all thoſe <hi>Interfering</hi> Lines concur to make up a perfect <hi>Beauty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For that over-ruling Hand that brought <hi>Light</hi> out of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> will bring <hi>Good</hi> out of <hi>Evil,</hi> and order the <hi>Worſt</hi> to the <hi>Beſt,</hi> for thoſe that love and fear him, if they'l but have a little patience to ſtay Gods leiſure: God ſends thee (it may be) many Changes, and often turns thee: It is but leaſt thou ſhouldeſt be (like <hi>Ephraim</hi>) a Cake <hi>half bak'd,</hi> unturn'd; He would have thee bak'd on both ſides; 'tis the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets expreſſion, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.8. And the Prophet <hi>David</hi> gives it in as a Pregnant Reaſon, why wicked Men are ſo wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.19. <hi>Becauſe they have no Changes, therefore they fear not God:</hi> Whereas thoſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106837:7"/>whom the World was not <hi>Worthy,</hi> had nothing of the worlds <hi>Worth,</hi> being deſtitute, Afflicted, Tormented; for as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, they had ſcarce a place to ſtand in, no more then their Lord and Maſter, who had not where to lay his <hi>Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence we may conclude, as alſo from this days bemoaned inſtance, that Affliction is, <hi>Innocentiae genius,</hi> as <hi>Calvin</hi> phraſeth it, The bad Angel that dogs Innocence at the heels; This Life being the good Mans Houſe of Correction.</p>
               <p>For here God keeps but his <hi>Petty Seſſions,</hi> Puniſhes many times the leaſt Offenders, <hi>Deferring</hi> the Tryal and Execution of the grand <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents,</hi> till the great <hi>Aſſize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And who need envy the plentiful feeding of the Fatned Hog, or Stall-fed Ox, deſign'd for the <hi>Shambles?</hi> Or the proſperous ſucceſs of <hi>Blood-guilty</hi> Men, who have but a <hi>Life-Eſtate</hi> on't at beſt; tho' uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Bloody and Deceitful Men do not live out <hi>half their days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What got the <hi>Roman</hi> Hero's by all their ſucceſsful Slaughters, but <hi>the ſame meaſure they meted out to others?</hi> as our Saviour Propheſies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               <p>For of all the Bloody <hi>Caeſars,</hi> till <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, 'tis truly ſpoken, what in God's juſt Judgments has prov'd as true to moſt of thoſe Blood-guilty Horſe-Leaches, concern'd in the Murder of our bleſſed Soveraign, That few, or none, went down to the Grave in Peace.</p>
               <p>There is a Divine <hi>Nemeſis</hi> that uſually in this Life haunts Injuſtice and Murder, and follows them at the heels, verified upon thoſe unjuſt <hi>Judges,</hi> which our <hi>Chronicles</hi> mention; Judge <hi>Morgan</hi> who Condemn'd the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> Judge <hi>Belknap,</hi> who confeſt in his Conſcience, when he ſign'd the Sentence, <hi>That there wanted nothing but a</hi> Hurdle, <hi>a</hi> Horſe, <hi>a</hi> Halter, <hi>and a</hi> Hangman <hi>to give him his due;</hi> and he afterwards had it in full meaſure, heaped up, and running over. That I mention not Later Inſtances, with which your Memories, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion can this day ſufficiently furniſh you; the Sunſhine of Villanous ſucceſs only Ripening their Sins for the Wine Preſs of the wrath of God; on whom was verified that Scripture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.17. <hi>The Eye that mocketh at his Father,</hi> (meant of the Father of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as well as our Natural Fathers) <hi>and deſpiſeth to Obey his Mother, the Ravens of the Valley ſhall pick it out,</hi> that is, he ſhall (according to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Deut. 21.20.) be put to Death, and his Unburi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Carcaſe be expos'd to the Fowls of the Air, to the Ravens.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106837:8"/>
               <p> The firſt thing that Ravenous Birds do to Carcaſes, is to pick out their Eyes.</p>
               <p>And he that ſheds a tear at ſuch juſter Execut ons, does (in this Sence) juſtly too forfeit his Eyes.</p>
               <p>So true it is in this particular, what was made good upon <hi>Ahab,</hi> for the Blood-ſhed mentioned in the Text, <hi>In the place where Dogs licked the Blood of</hi> Naboth; <hi>ſhall Dogs lick thy Blood, even thine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus within a very little while did God Revenge the Blood of <hi>Jezreel</hi> upon the houſe of <hi>Jehu,</hi> and the Blood of our Bleſſed Martyr upon his Murtherers; who, as Beaſts Crowned for a Sacrifice, were rais'd to that Uſurping heighth, that they might be tumbled down with the more dreadful downfal. The Air is moſt quiet and ſerene a little before an <hi>Earthquake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, tho' the Revenging ſtroke of God's Juſtice ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ the juſter Execution of <hi>Rapacious</hi> Men in this Life, I would be loath to Eat of their Dainties, to pay their after reckoning.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Does the beſt of Men many times meet with the worſt of Uſage in this Life? Then let us make the ſame good uſe of the worſt of uſage, that God intends us by ſuch Uſages; namely, that by being Batter'd by them, we may be Better'd by them.</p>
               <p>God Grant that the Bitter Doſes that <hi>England</hi> has lately taken, may ſo Purge its ill Humours, that its Conſtitution may be more Sound and Healthful, than thoſe Valetudinary ill boding Symptomes yet viſible in its Face does Promiſe.</p>
               <p>Its Hypocritical Look is but a ſad Prognoſtick; a Mortal Look, as if we might read Death in its Face: God avert the <hi>Criſis,</hi> and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Paroxiſme: Shall I not viſit for theſe things? Shall not my Soul be Avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God's will be done; it may be more Miſeries may do us more God, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men (like the <hi>Athenians</hi>) may look beſt in Black.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>England</hi> never looks well, but when in a Weeping Poſture. Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Habits do beſt become her. <hi>In their Affliction they will ſeek me Early.</hi> 'Tis poſſible we may then be beſt, when 'tis worſt with us; and Thrive, like <hi>Camomile,</hi> the better for being ſat upon. The State of a good Man in this Life, being very well Emblematically Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that of the Palm-Tree, with this Motto, <hi>Depreſſa Reſurgo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Weights that are hung upon him makes him Grow the Better.</p>
               <p>Indeed no Chaſtiſement for the preſent ſeemeth Joyous, but Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous; nevertheleſs afterwards it yieldeth the Peaceable Fruit of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106837:8"/>Righteouſneſs to them that are Exerciſed thereby. What matter tho' the Storm be Violent, ſo it ſpeed us the ſooner to our Port? What though you be waſhed in the <hi>Jordan</hi> of Affliction ſeven times, ſo you be Cured of your <hi>Leproſie?</hi> Wormwood is wholeſome, though it be Bitter. <hi>He that Sowes in Tears, ſhall Reap in Joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tears are the beſt Holy Water to drive away the Devil. <hi>It is good for me that I have been Afflicted,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>David,</hi> repeating his experiences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almond</hi> Trees are made more Fruitful by driving Nails into them, which lets out a Noxious Gum, which would otherwiſe hinder its Fruitfulneſs. Some ſuch advantage Saint <hi>Paul</hi> found by the Pricks in the Fleſh; on which account it is that Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> Triumphs in his, as Scars of Honour; Oh, <hi>Felices Tribulos Tribulationum!</hi> Oh, <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Thorns of Tribulation,</hi> that lets out my Impoſtumes!</p>
               <p>The Shower of Stones ſent St. <hi>Stephen</hi> faſter to Heaven. Enemies may Kill, but cannot Hurt: And though the Children of <hi>Belial</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd our Bleſſed Martyr of His Head, they could not Rob Him of His Crown. (To uſe His own Heavenly Words) <q>I ſhall not want Heavy and Envyed Crowns of this World, when My God hath Mercifully Crown'd and Conſummated His Graces with Glory, and Exchang'd the Shadows of My Earthly Kingdomes among Men, for the Subſtance of that Heavenly Kingdom with Himſelf.</q>
               </p>
               <p>God never ſtrikes down his People, but (as we do a <hi>Tennis-Ball</hi> upon the Pavement) that it may Mount and Rebound the higher. Thus he permitted Wicked Men to ſtrike at, and ſtrike down our Bleſſed Martyr'd Sovereign, that he might Exalt Him in His own Throne, and in the Hearts and Memory of all that are truly Pious. <hi>Pungit, Deinde <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngit.</hi> God firſt let Afflictions cloſe up to the Swords Point, before he did Anoint him with the Oyl of gladneſs above his Fellows.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>The Second Obſervation is,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THAT the Rabble and Multitude are many times, thro' Zeal for Religion and Juſtice, Guilty of horrid Impieties:</hi> As in the Text, <hi>(They) Stoned him.</hi> Where the word <hi>(They) Concords</hi> with the foregoing word <hi>(the People)</hi> the unjuſt Judges <hi>Condemn</hi> Innocent <hi>Naboth</hi> in the Preſence of the People; and they, the People, turn <hi>Executioners,</hi> and hurry him away without any more ado, out of the City, and <hi>Stoned him with Stones, that he Died.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106837:9"/>
               <p> Thus the Rabble in a Tumult, (like Dogs in a chafe) Bite and Bark at their Maſters, and Friends, as well as at their Foes.</p>
               <p>All's alike; as here, <hi>Naboth</hi> hurt them not, had given no juſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; but that's all one, he was Accus'd for Blaſphemy; and they took it for granted to be true, being Gull'd by Politick Stateſmen, with the Pretences of Juſtice and Devotion. Thus Zeal Miſguided, like a Horſe without a Bridle, may run faſt enough, but out of the Way, making more Haſte then good Speed: Or, like Fire out of the Hearth, which uſually does harm; Warms not, but Conſumes.</p>
               <p>Thus Politicians that Plot Rebellion, and Mutiny, do but give out a Religious <hi>Watch-Word,</hi> and the People ſtraight give the Word about, and are up in Arms for God and his Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Thus when a wicked Grandee begins a Health, ſome or other of the Rabble will Pledge it, tho' it be Blood: As in this woful inſtance of the Text and the Day: Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> do <hi>Strenue Calumniari,</hi> accuſe falſly and impudently; and Swear hard, and the People believe them; and cry, as in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s caſe, <hi>Away with ſuch a Fellow from the Earth, for it is not fit that he ſhould Live.</hi> And why? They knew not; for the moſt of them knew not why they were met together; indocible Crew! that leſt Equity and Juſtice ſhould carry it at a fair hearing, they ſtop their Ears, as they did at St. <hi>Stephens</hi> Tryal, and run upon him with one accord.</p>
               <p>Thus did they furiouſly noiſe it againſt our Saviour, <hi>Crucifie Him, Crucifie Him;</hi> and tho' <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> who was more Sober, would have them make a Halt, and tell firſt, what <hi>Evil hath he done?</hi> Yet they cryed out the more, like an Impetuous <hi>Torrent</hi> that ſwells when 'tis Damm'd, right or wrong, <hi>Let Him be Crucified, let him be Crucified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ſoon were the Fickle Jews weary of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, that at firſt flock'd to him? All <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and all <hi>Judea,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.5. <hi>We'll have a King,</hi> ſay the People to <hi>Samuel;</hi> and then preſently after, the ſame People change their Notes, <hi>We have added to our Iniquity this more, in asking us a King,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. The preſent Government is always Grievous to them; like Weathercocks, who tho' always mutable, yet always ſet their Faces againſt, and brave that Wind that is moſt Potent.</p>
               <p>The Vulgar, <hi>Reuben</hi> like, are Unſtable as water, and one day cry, <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> to Chriſt, and the next day, <hi>Crucifie Him:</hi> In the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to fall down, adore, and deifie <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Acts</hi> 14.18. And in v. 19. Being tickled in the Ear with another Story,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106837:9"/>that certain Jews that came from <hi>Antioch, They ſtoned</hi> Paul, <hi>and drew him out of the City, ſuppoſing he had been dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Subtile Uſurpers thus, like <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> make <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Sin; and by pretending a <hi>Cheaper</hi> way of Devotion, and a nearer <hi>cut</hi> then going up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> entice them to <hi>worſhip</hi> their Golden <hi>Calves</hi> in <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> thô the <hi>lowest of the people be the Priests;</hi> and to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the Abomination, the Uſurper himſelf became <hi>one of the Priests of the high places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus theſe impetuous Torrents (like the Tydes by the paler Moon) are Influenced, and led about to and fro, as their pious <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi>'s that Head them, ſhall Animate and Direct; but are eſpecially Charm'd (like <hi>Bees,</hi> when they are up in a Swarm) by the tinckling Noiſe of Reformation and Liberty.</p>
               <p>Yet many times when theſe Swarms are <hi>up,</hi> no body knows where they will <hi>alight,</hi> nor they themſelves well; the <hi>Fiends</hi> ſometimes, for want of work, falls upon the <hi>Conjurers</hi> that <hi>rais'd</hi> them. And 'tis but juſt that theſe <hi>Bearwards</hi> ſhould ſometimes (for Example ſake) be worried by their own Whelps, and they are but right ſerved; 'tis Good enough for ſo Bad a Trade.</p>
               <p>'Twas this tumultuous Wild-fire that firſt ſet our flouriſhing Kingdom on a Flame, kindled and blown up by the buſie Lungs of fomenting Incendiaries, little regarding the miſchievous Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Flames, ſo they might Warm their own Hands: <hi>Nero</hi> like, Solacing and Sporting themſelves, when the City was on Fire.</p>
               <p>But I am Tired with the unpleaſing Thoughts of theſe Horrors, and ſhall therefore put an end to this Diſcourſe of Tumults. God grant our Tumults may be at an end!</p>
               <p>I proceed now to the Third and laſt Obſervation, which I eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aim'd at, when I choſe this Text, ſo ſutable it is to the preſent Occaſion; and it is taken from the firſt and laſt Words of the Text, <hi>compared</hi> together; <hi>They proclaimed a Fast, and Stoned him with Stones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence Obſerve.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>That the most black and bloody Villanies are uſually Varniſh'd with Religion and Juſtice.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>A Truth that (God knows) needs no Proof to thoſe whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories can furniſh them (by this Day's doleful Celebration) with a lamentable Inſtance, though I ſhould not mention <hi>this</hi> in the Text.</p>
               <p>The Cry of Religion and Juſtice, Conſcience, and the Cauſe of God, giving Hoſanna's to one of the <hi>bloodiest</hi> Butcheries, that the moſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106837:10"/>diſmal Night did e'er give Midwifery unto, or the affrighted Sun ever ſaw.</p>
               <p>Making the ſame uſe of <hi>the Goſpel, the Goſpel,</hi> to compaſs the <hi>barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Deſigns, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did of their Temple; exclaiming, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord;</hi> which the diviner Prophet call'd, <hi>Lying words,</hi> Jer. 7.4. and Suits too well with a Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Lyars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Hypocritical Flouriſh of the mentioned <hi>Jews,</hi> not eſcaping the more <hi>prying</hi> Conſideration of an Heathen <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who, upon this Score, well ſtyled the <hi>Jews</hi> Temple, <hi>Impiae gentis Arcanum,</hi> A Sanctuary of Roguery. <hi>Avouching</hi> their <hi>malignant</hi> Hatred (as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> records) with <hi>The Lord be glorified, the Lord be glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Voice, is the Voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but the Hands! <hi>the Hands are the Hands of</hi> Eſau.</p>
               <p>I ſhall name but Two ſpecial <hi>Reaſons</hi> of this Obſervation, before I make a cloſer <hi>Application.</hi> And the Firſt is this:</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>Bloody</hi> Villanies are commonly <hi>Varniſh'd</hi> with <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> that the horrid Projects may take the more proſperous Effect: For even good, and well meaning Men may be proſelyted to a Deviliſh Faction, if the Conjurers, when they raiſe it, can make it appear like an <hi>Angel of light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe <hi>Witches</hi> of <hi>Endor</hi> always <hi>raiſing</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> in the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of a <hi>Prophet.</hi> For, if the Devil ſhould appear in his own horrid <hi>Shape,</hi> he would Fright even thoſe that Study this <hi>Black Art.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Diſmal and Bloody Villanies are Varniſh'd with Religion, that upon Diſappointments, they may not altogether be Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For, if the Cockatrice-Egg of Sedition, be not Hatch'd with the Warmth of a Conventicle, into the Serpent of Rebellion, then it muſt paſs for a harmleſs <hi>Incubation.</hi> Thus horrid <hi>Faux,</hi> ſurpriz'd in his <hi>deſtructive Cells,</hi> retains his Vizor, pleads he is about his Lawful Occaſions, means no <hi>Harm,</hi> not he; may not <hi>he</hi> and his Confederates <hi>meet</hi> in their own hired Houſe? Has the King's Officers no more Conſcience, than to Diſturb Honeſt Men? Thus the <hi>old</hi> Powder-Plotters, and Underminers of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> did not want the <hi>ſame</hi> Apologies of our <hi>modern</hi> Faux<hi>'s.</hi> So that, thô the Train they have laid, to Blow up at once the Church and State, do not take, yet they are Shot-free, and Juſtice-proof by a pious Charm.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Man-ſlayers,</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> makes mention of in his time, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.5. uſed the very ſame Canting Tone of our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106837:10"/>
                  <hi>men of blood,</hi> of a later date; <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord, bleſſed be the Lord:</hi> And yet in the foregoing Words of the ſame Verſe, 'tis recorded, <hi>That they Slew the Innocent, and Sold others,</hi> and yet held <hi>themſelves not Guilty.</hi> Read but <hi>that</hi> Scripture, and you need not ſtudy a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel Inſtance.</p>
               <p>So that thô theſe pious <hi>Panders,</hi> cannot in the <hi>Night</hi> of <hi>Deluſion,</hi> Proſtitute their deformed <hi>Brats,</hi> and monſtrous <hi>Conceptions,</hi> unto the blacker Villanies they Luſt after, and are in Love with, yet the <hi>Changeling</hi> ſtill retains the Name of a <hi>Babe of Grace,</hi> and ſo may paſs, if not for a <hi>Beauty,</hi> yet for a <hi>Saint;</hi> or at leaſt <hi>ſtave</hi> off, for fear of doing Violence to <hi>Purity,</hi> all thoughts of Searching her for a <hi>Witch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wandring</hi> Vagabonds do thus <hi>legitimate</hi> their <hi>Vagrancy</hi> by a <hi>Ballad,</hi> or <hi>Pedling Trade;</hi> which thô it bring not much in, yet it ſaves their Backs from the Brand due to <hi>Rogues.</hi> And thô to Pick mens Pockets be the main Deſign, yet miſſing their Aim, they may Finger ſome ſmall <hi>Pence</hi> by a <hi>Canting</hi> Tone; <hi>Looking</hi> (like <hi>Watermen</hi>) one way, and <hi>Rowing</hi> another; and yet <hi>take it ill,</hi> that Men will not believe they are going <hi>Sion</hi>-wards, becauſe their Faces are thitherwards. For the Villany was no ſooner perpetrated, but (as <hi>Tamar</hi> after ſhe had <hi>plaid</hi> her wicked <hi>Prank,</hi> reſumed the Garment of her <hi>Widowhood</hi>) they <hi>Robed</hi> themſelves again with the Old <hi>Veſtment</hi> and <hi>Coverlid of Sanctity;</hi> hung down the Head like a Bul-ruſh; look'd Sadly; and, with the Whore in the <hi>Proverbs, Wiped their Mouthes, and ſaid, they had done no Wickedneſs.</hi> So that if the Uſherage of Sanctity cannot hand in their black Deformities of Rapine, Blood, and Sacriledge, which they ſo much <hi>Court;</hi> yet it will ſerve to Fence off the Stroke of Juſtice, due to Thieves and Murtherers; or at worſt, <hi>Canonize</hi> them for Saints and Martyrs in the bloody <hi>Kalender</hi> of their own <hi>Crew.</hi> But 'tis well known, by the Blows they Strike, what they Aim at, thô, at the ſame time, they look another way.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> like <hi>Iſhmael</hi> the Son of <hi>Nethaniah,</hi> Meditate a Slaughter, thô they may (as he did, a little before he <hi>Slew</hi> the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Men) ſhed a few <hi>Crocodile</hi> Tears; the Text ſays, he came <hi>weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all along as he went,</hi> Jer. 41.6. And the next Verſe records the <hi>Butchery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to apply this home to the preſent Occaſion, (for we muſt not thus have done with it) we'll ſee if we can, pull the <hi>Vizor</hi> of this <hi>Faux,</hi> and rather <hi>Rub</hi> hard to get off the <hi>Paint,</hi> than that <hi>Jezabel</hi> ſhould paſs for a <hi>Beauty,</hi> leſt we Sin by <hi>Connivance,</hi> as did the <hi>Church</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106837:11"/>of <hi>Thyatira.</hi> God grant, that our Lord Jeſus do not Write <hi>bitter things against this Nation,</hi> for <hi>this</hi> Sin, as <hi>he</hi> did againſt his beloved Church of <hi>Thyatira;</hi> and that this Epidemical Sin bring not upon us another Epidemical Plague, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I have a few things against thee, becauſe thou ſufferest that woman</hi> Jezabel <hi>to teach and to ſeduce my Servants; to commit Fornication, and to commit Murther, Rapine, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge.</hi> I now come to the Application.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If diſmal and bloody Villanies be commonly <hi>Varniſh'd</hi> with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> then this may Inform us, That the moſt <hi>plauſible Pretexts</hi> of Religion are always <hi>Suſpicious,</hi> ſince ſo ſeldom <hi>Sincere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt tells us ſo of the <hi>Puritan</hi> Sect amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> called <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> that they might <hi>gorge</hi> themſelves with the <hi>tears</hi> of <hi>Orphans,</hi> and <hi>devour Widows Houſes,</hi> with more <hi>eaſe,</hi> and leſs <hi>danger.</hi> They went to Prayer, nay, made <hi>long Prayers,</hi> as <hi>Jezabel</hi> did in the Text; <hi>prologues</hi> the Murther with a <hi>Proclamation</hi> for a Religious, Solemn, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Fast.</hi> I need not tell you, that the Murtherers of our Sovereign <hi>writ</hi> directly after this <hi>copy, tract</hi> the ſame <hi>paths, wrought</hi> with <hi>the</hi> ſame <hi>inſtruments,</hi> and <hi>effected</hi> the ſame Cruelty, with the very ſame <hi>methods</hi> of Piety and Juſtice, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.5.6. <hi>When ye faſted and wept every month, did ye all fast unto me? Even unto me?</hi> Did you <hi>macerate</hi> your Bodies, that your keener Stomachs might take the larger Draught of innocent Blood?</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> a kind of <hi>mungrel</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>barbarous</hi> People, and Bordering upon <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> living wholly upon Rapine, always <hi>pray to Christ</hi> in the Morning, to make them Diligent in their Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and help them to good Booty: So the wild <hi>Iriſh</hi> never went a Maſs-trooping, but with the Auſpiciums of a <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and <hi>Ave Maria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus theſe grand Rebels in <hi>Richard</hi> the Second's time, <hi>Prefac'd</hi> all their <hi>Letters</hi> to their <hi>Confederates,</hi> with whom they held <hi>Intelligence</hi> in the <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> with theſe Heavenly words, <hi>Glory be to God on high, on earth peace, good will towards men.</hi> Strange Confidence! What? <hi>Glory to God,</hi> when their own Conſciences told them they were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving the Ruine of ſuch as the Majeſty of Heaven calls, <hi>Gods upon Earth!</hi> And, <hi>peace on earth,</hi> when they were Meditating a <hi>War!</hi> And, <hi>good will towards men,</hi> when they were going about to <hi>Cut their Throats!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is like <hi>Joab</hi>'s Complement; <hi>Art thou in Health, my Brother?</hi> And then follows the <hi>Kiſs</hi> with a <hi>Stab.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106837:11"/>
               <p> Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VI. was ſo known a Diſſembler in his time, that afterwards it became a <hi>Proverb</hi> in <hi>Rome, When his Holineſs Swears, you may Swear 'tis falſe. England</hi> may well ſay, that her Royal <hi>Head</hi> was then firſt <hi>ſtruck at,</hi> when the Executioners <hi>entred into Covenant,</hi> more <hi>ſolemnly</hi> to <hi>Swear its Preſervation;</hi> as if the Breaking of <hi>former</hi> Oaths of Allegiance, could not ſpeak them ſufficiently Perfidious and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal, but they muſt call Heaven and Earth to Witneſs <hi>afreſh</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled</hi> Perjuries; or elſe reſolved to Contradict the Truth of that Scripture in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.12. <hi>A threefold cord is not eaſily broken,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as their poor, weak, and tender Conſciences, could Snap them with eaſe, and make nothing of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cataline</hi> begun his <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> with a <hi>Covenant</hi> and a bloody <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Theſe <hi>Judas</hi>'s are then moſt likely to <hi>betray,</hi> when they come to <hi>ſalute, Caveatur oſculum Iſcarioticum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Proverbially ſay, when the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſends them an <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> for Peace, <hi>Claude foras,</hi> they are certain <hi>then</hi> they muſt <hi>Fight</hi> for't. I could apply it to as ſmooth a Tongu'd Generation; and if not ſo Subtile, yet they are as Falſe, and can Play with Oaths, as Monkeys with their Collars, can put them <hi>on</hi> and <hi>off</hi> as they liſt. <hi>Pro Rege, Lege, Grege,</hi> was the common <hi>Motto</hi> in thoſe days, what they meant by the firſt Word, <hi>this</hi> Day's Remembrance does too truly Admoniſh us; <hi>Is this thy kindneſs to thy friend?</hi> In which religious Treachery, they did but much reſemble that <hi>jugling</hi> Pope before-mentioned, and his Son <hi>Caeſar Borgias,</hi> of whom it was ſaid, <hi>That one never ſpoke as he thought, and the other never performed what he ſpake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this <hi>Senſe</hi> we may ſay of our <hi>Martyr'd</hi> Sovereign, what <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Caeſar</hi> at his <hi>fall;</hi> His pretended <hi>Friends,</hi> not his <hi>Enemies</hi> tumbled him down. And how many Wretches might our glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Martyr have juſtly Upbraided with the ſame Words that <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his laſt Words <hi>groaned</hi> out to his Son <hi>Brutus? What! and thou, my Son, too!</hi> Thou, my Subject! Thou that haſt ſworn <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and confirmed it again with a <hi>Covenant</hi> of a later date! Have we not Cauſe, more than enough, to uſe that good Man's <hi>Letany,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of our Sovereign and theſe Kingdoms, <hi>Libera nos ab amicis:</hi> From ſuch Friends, good Lord deliver us?</p>
               <p>'Twas <hi>capital,</hi> even amongſt the ruder <hi>Scythians,</hi> if any did <hi>Duo peccata contorquere, make a Pleat of two Sins together;</hi> as Lie, and Swear to it. The moſt barbarous Nations have Outvied us in Honeſty:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106837:12"/>For, whilſt ſuch a Stir was made to <hi>make Room</hi> for Religion, good Nature has been <hi>juſtled</hi> out; and we have loſt <hi>Humanity</hi> and <hi>Morals.</hi> And the <hi>very Heathen ſhall riſe up in judgment against us.</hi> The Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patetick owned more Divinity in his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> where he ſays, <hi>It is not good for a man to diſſent from the Gods, his Father, or his Teacher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>new</hi> Goſpellers, thô they do <hi>not walk</hi> much like Chriſtians, yet will <hi>talk</hi> like them. This <hi>lip</hi> Religion is ſo <hi>cheap</hi> and <hi>eaſie</hi> to be come by, that every Hypocrite can afford to <hi>diſciple</hi> himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; but, when it comes to Works of Charity, and to Evidence a true Faith by good Works, then <hi>vale lumen amicum;</hi> Goſpel-Light and he muſt <hi>ſhake hands,</hi> and part.</p>
               <p>The greateſt <hi>Talkers</hi> are ſeldom the greateſt <hi>Doers.</hi> The Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask Roſe is more <hi>Fragrant,</hi> but not ſo <hi>Cordial</hi> as the Red. And thoſe days, whoſe bloody. <hi>Hew</hi> will <hi>ſtain</hi> the Chronicle to all Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, have yet been Cryed up for the <hi>Goſpel-days;</hi> whereas if we <hi>view</hi> but the Murthers, Sacriledge, and Rapine, which theſe Goſpellers did <hi>perpetrate,</hi> we muſt ſay, as that Learned <hi>Lanacre</hi> did, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſtraighter and directer Rules, and Goſpel-Lines, deſcrib'd in Chriſt's Sermon upon the Mount, with thoſe more <hi>crooked</hi> and <hi>perverſe</hi> Draughts of the men of his times; <hi>Either this is not Goſpel, or we are not Goſpellers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sure I am, that this Day's ſad <hi>Inſtance</hi> gives us Occaſion to <hi>put it to the queſtion,</hi> (as of Old to the jugling <hi>Jews,</hi> that profaned God's holy Name, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.20.) <hi>Are theſe the people of the Lord that came forth of his Land?</hi> Do you take his Name in Vain, <hi>Motley</hi> Chriſtians? Do ye take Chriſt's Name in Vain? Such <hi>Iſraelites</hi> as theſe have too much <hi>guile</hi> in them to be <hi>Nathanaels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More like that <hi>Iſrael</hi> (mentioned by the Prophet) which was but an empty Vine, that only <hi>brought forth fruit unto it ſelf. Vox &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea nihil,</hi> as he ſaid of the <hi>Nightingale,</hi> nothing but a <hi>Noiſe.</hi> The <hi>emptiest</hi> Kettle makes the greateſt <hi>ſound;</hi> and the moſt <hi>lewd</hi> are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the moſt <hi>loud.</hi> And we may truly reprove ſuch (in the words of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> to that vitious <hi>Antipater,</hi> that <hi>bipedum nequiſſimus,</hi> who wore a white Cloak in token of Innocency) <hi>virtutis ſtragulum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defacitis,</hi> ye make Religion <hi>bluſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To uſe the words of the Prophet <hi>Micah, Do ye build up Zion with blood, and Religion with iniquity?</hi> And yet lean upon the Lord, and ſay, <hi>Is not the Lord among us? No evil can come unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106837:12"/>
               <p> The little attendance on this Day's Celebration in this populous City, who can, at other times, throng in a <hi>Crowd,</hi> to the want of <hi>Elbow-room,</hi> makes me with grief of heart preſume, That the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood ſhed upon this Day, is but little upon the Hearts, and too little a Grief of Heart to many, that I ſay not <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who can not only coldly neglect their Duty herein, without remorſe, but even dare to appear in Publick againſt the Celebration of this neceſſary <hi>Fast;</hi> as if there was now no <hi>need</hi> of <hi>keeping</hi> it. Theſe are ſuch whoſe Fathers <hi>acted</hi> this Murder; and they bring their Fathers Guilt upon themſelves by <hi>juſtifying</hi> it. Nor is this all, for ſince the late Revolution, there are ſome that in <hi>Print</hi> have gone about to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame the Royal Martyr, (and, as it were, Murder him again) by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that he was <hi>no Martyr;</hi> and that his Pious and Excellent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, (which, perhaps, next to the Holy Bible, is <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>best</hi> Books in the World) are <hi>none</hi> of his; but they bear his <hi>Portraicture</hi> too much to be Suſpected by any honeſt Man, notwithſtanding all that the <hi>Spawn</hi> of the Regicides do affirm to the contrary; who have alſo the Impudence to affirm, that <hi>A King is the Creature of the People;</hi> and therefore they may do what they will with him. Does this look like Repentance for the Innocent Blood that was <hi>ſhed</hi> upon this Day? No ſurely: Theſe Men cannot find Leiſure for this great and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Employ, in ſolemnly Deprecating that divine Vengeance, which I fear is yet <hi>due</hi> to ſo Impenitent a <hi>Crew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> are loſt upon ſuch: For, as all truly generous Spirits do look upon an irreconcilable Implacability as Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and Unmanly, as well as Unchriſtian; ſo an impenitent and ſtubborn Diſobedience (like the Sin of <hi>Witchcraft</hi>) is Helliſh and Devilliſh. <hi>Errare humanum est, perſeverare Diabolicum. Will ye ſteal and kill,</hi> ſaith the Prophet: [In the <hi>Hebrew] Will ye ſtealing ſteal, and murthering murther, and yet come into this houſe, which is called by my Name, and ſay, we are delivered to do all theſe Abominations?</hi> Procul hinc procul ite prophani. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices unto me? ſaith the Lord. When you come to appear before me, who hath required this at your hands, to tread my Courts?</hi> Does Piety and Purity prompt you to Sacriledge? Does your Fear of God keep you from Repentance? Does your Fear of God keep you from Honouring your King?</p>
               <p>This was <hi>Becket</hi>'s Plea; he would ſubmit to his Sovereign with <hi>ae ſalvo honore Dei:</hi> He was Content not to be a Rebel, ſo that his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106837:13"/>Allegiance might not <hi>diſhonour</hi> God. <hi>Good man!</hi> His Conſcience was Tender of God's Glory, but Seared at the thought of <hi>peace on earth, and good will towards men.</hi> Is your inſatiable Boulimies not yet Glutted? But muſt you again Puddle our Waters, that you may Fiſh the better? But I have had too much Occaſion to Enlarge upon this Head. I'll name but one Particular more, and come to a Concluſion; and that is, an Uſe of <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſince <hi>black</hi> and <hi>bloody</hi> Villanies are uſually <hi>Varniſh'd</hi> with Religion, let us not mind mens <hi>Pretences,</hi> but their <hi>Practices. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> himſelf could not have ſpoken more Divinely, than did the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in his Likeneſs. How ill does the Language of <hi>Canaan</hi> become the Inhabitants of <hi>Hell?</hi> Peace in the Mouth, and War in the Heart: As if theſe Pretenders to the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did reſolve to avouch their Claim thereunto, by being like the Old <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name</hi> ſignifies <hi>Peace,</hi> and yet no ſuch <hi>Slaughter</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> in any City of the World. <hi>Mel in ore verba lactis, fel in corde fraus in factis,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt does Engliſh it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.21.</p>
               <p>The Tomb-ſtone may have a fair Motto, and ſpecious Out-ſide; but what's underneath? <hi>Bleſſed be thou of the Lord,</hi> ſays <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, I have kept the commandment of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.13, 14, 15. <hi>Hast thou ſo?</hi> ſaith <hi>Samuel,</hi> then <hi>What mean this bleating of the Sheep in mine ears, and the lowing of the Oxen which I hear? Oh,</hi> ſaith the Sycophant, <hi>they are to ſacrifice to the Lord thy God.</hi> So: Are our Pretenders to Love, Loyalty, Obedience and Peace, indeed ſo much for <hi>Peace,</hi> and for performing the <hi>Commandments of the Lord?</hi> Then what means that <hi>Shimei</hi>'s Bleating, and <hi>Rabſhekah</hi>'s Railing againſt this bleſſed Martyr, which I hear? What means the Rapine, and Sacriledge, (which is ſo far from being repented of) that 'tis again endeavour'd to be Repeated? Will you ſay, 'Tis to Sacrifice to the Lord your God? <hi>Behold to obey is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of Rams; for rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraft, and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is as iniquity and idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>You may never expect (ſaith our bleſſed Martyr to his Eldeſt Son, K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. who alſo found it true) leſs of Loyalty, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Humanity, then from thoſe that engage into a Religious Rebellion; their Intereſt is made God's, under the Colours of Piety. Ambitious Policies march not only with greateſt Security, but Applauſe, as to the Popularity. You may hear from them <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Voice, but you ſhall ſee they have <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Hands.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106837:13"/>
               <p> Come, pull off that Bullruſh-Coat, it has been worn too long: the Plot is ſo ſtale, that I can ſcarce think any in this Age, who has not loſt his Pallate, can longer Reliſh it. What Rebels ſhall be hereafter, muſt needs be ſo upon Malice fore-thought: the mournful Hiſtory of thoſe Calamities, that uſhered in this fatal Day, [that Volumn writ in Blood!] let us underſtand your Meanings, whatever be your Language, or your Title-Page. Thoſe horrid Inſtruments found in your <hi>Faux</hi>'s Cellars, unriddle the Meanings of your Meeting, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your Buſh does promiſe. The Whore in the Proverbs began her Sorceries with Peace-Offerings, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.14. <hi>God is near in your mouth</hi> (as the Prophet ſaith) <hi>but far from your Reins. Ye ſhall not fast as ye do this day, to make your voice to be heard on high. Is it ſuch a Fast that I have choſen? A day for a man to afflict his ſoul? Is it to down bow his head as a bulruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes under him? wilt thou call this a Fast, and an acceptable day to the Lord? Behold ye fast for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fist of wickedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Edomites</hi> are right father-like, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41. <hi>The days of mourning for my Father are at hand, then will I ſlay my Brother</hi> Jacob. The Days ſet apart for the pious Solemnity of his Father's Funeral, was the fitteſt time for him to execute his bloody Malice upon his Brother. The Text ſays, <hi>He was detained before the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 21.7. <hi>Sacris abutitur ut ſceleratis mos est.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus alſo does the <hi>Edomite,</hi> when he meditated the Slaughter of the Prieſts of the Lord, which he afterwards effected, he was at his Devotions.</p>
               <p>This Day reminds us too Evidently, who uſed the ſame Methods of Cruelty, and with whoſe Royal Blood thoſe eager Horſe-Leach's did gorge themſelves, after they had firſt paid their Devotions, ſought the Lord, and Grace once ſaid, they fell on to their bloody Banquet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> bleſs'd God when he was going to <hi>Rome</hi> to be Martyred, to think that his Blood ſhould be found among the Worthies, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. under the Altar, crying with a loud Voice, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true, dost thou not judge, and avenge our Blood on them that dwell on the Earth;</hi> and that God making Inquiſition for Blood, would ſearch for the Blood of Righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> to the Blood of <hi>Barachias,</hi> and alſo down as low as mean <hi>Ignatius.</hi> And (I will add) when God ſits upon the Grand Inqueſt for innocent Blood, He will not only Search as low as mean <hi>Ignatius,</hi> but righteous <hi>Charles,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106837:14"/>(to the immortal Honour and Diſhonour of our Nation) <hi>England</hi>'s Martyr.</p>
               <p>Our Kingdom has been famous over the World, for the firſt Chriſtian King in the World, <hi>Lucius;</hi> for the firſt Chriſtian Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the World, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; for the firſt Reformed Prince, K. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. and for the firſt Royal Martyr for the Church and State, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. choſing rather to reſiſt to Blood, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the Laws of the Land, the Freedom and Honour of Parliaments, the Rights of His Crown, the juſt Liberty of his Subjects, and the true Chriſtian Religion in its Doctrin, Government, and due En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, to the greedy Jaws of ravening Wolves. <hi>A good Shepherd giveth his Life for the Sheep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſt deſervedly therefore, as the <hi>Romans</hi> did their Emperour <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> may we Stile him, (without ſuſpition of flattery) <hi>deliciae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani generis,</hi> the good Peoples Darling, an epidemical Cordial: <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum populi,</hi> as <hi>Scypio</hi> was called, the Peoples Sweet-Heart; who was <hi>De regione non magis ſollicitus quam de Religione;</hi> cared not ſo much for his own Kingdom as God's; counting it more Honour. (with the good Emperours, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) to be <hi>Chriſti vaſallam, &amp; membrum Eccleſiae, quam caput Imperii:</hi> Chriſt's Servants, than an Earthly King; and a Member of the Church, rather than Head of an Empire.</p>
               <p>Having cropt the Top of all Vertues, as <hi>Pindarus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hiero,</hi> or as <hi>Vitellius</hi> of <hi>Cato Major, Homo virtuti ſimillimus, optimus imperator, orator, Senator omniumque artium magiſter,</hi> he was as like Vertue as ever one could look, being an incomparable King, an incomparable Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, an incomparable States-man, and an incomparable Church-man; and if not, the endowments of a Prophet, yet of a King and Prieſt, being at all Eſſays a Maſter of Art. But in his juſter Praiſes, though Rhetorick it ſelf ſhould expatiate, ſhe muſt loſe a Figure, his worth tranſcending common Hyperboles. <hi>The Memory of the just is bleſſed,</hi> Prov. 10.7.</p>
               <p>A great Man good, is greatly good; not only becauſe they are precious by being rare, (for God knows) we may too often ſay of Religion (as it was ſaid of <hi>David) The Lords favour thee not,</hi> Sam. 29.6. (making it their buſineſs <hi>Erigere muros maris quam corrigere mores,</hi> to build Manners rather than to mend their Manners.) But becauſe their good Examples, as well as their bad, are greatly followed; like great Men, being the Looking-Glaſſes by which the Rabble dreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106837:14"/>the great Body turning to and fro, and if the Head turn round, the unwilely bulk will uſually wheel for Company.</p>
               <p>I love not Encomiums of this Nature; but here to be ſilent, is to injure Innocence, and rob a Righteous Man, a Righteous King, and a Glorious Martyr of his due. God himſelf calls a worſe King, his choice One, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nemo vir magnus ſine afflatu divino unquam fuit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cicero,</hi> no Man did ever do or ſuffer bravely, but by divine Inſtinct, a Hand lent him from Heaven; and I think it no boldneſs to ſay, (amongſt a People that think themſelves reproach'd, when <hi>Charles</hi> is vindicated) no Man could do or ſuffer (with that Chriſtian Patience, Meckneſs, and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity) the Impriſonments, and Tumults, the Reproaches, and Martyrdom that he did, except God was with him. Oh when will this Kingdom deſerve the title that (<hi>Polidore-Virgil</hi> ſays was once u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually given to it) <hi>Regnum Angliae, regnum Dei; Regnum Angliae, reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Angelorum;</hi> whilſt this day tells us, it was <hi>Regnum Diabolorum. Plato</hi> commends the Attick Country, in that it was beloved of God, and loved God. Oh that <hi>England</hi> might be ſo too; beloved of God, and love God, and fear God; which is impoſſible, if we do not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King; ſo ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.2. though cruel <hi>Nero</hi> had then the power: He <hi>that reſiſteth the Power is damned;</hi> or, (as our Tranſlation) <hi>ſhall receive to himſelf Damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Scripture, that I wonder how thoſe that glory ſo much in their poring upon the Scripture, can overlook; or their tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences make a baulk of, without either Scruple or Remorſe. So that we have <hi>cauſe</hi> to wiſh for our <hi>Kingdom,</hi> (as <hi>Ferus</hi> did for the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Synagogue) that we had ſome <hi>Moſes</hi> to take away our <hi>Evils; Non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim unum tantum vitulum, fed multos habemus, non tres Rebelles,</hi> Korah, Dathan, <hi>&amp;</hi> Abiram, <hi>fed innumeros.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had but one gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en <hi>Calf,</hi> but we have <hi>many; they</hi> had three grand Rebels, <hi>Korah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> but we <hi>thouſands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if Rebellion, with all its odious <hi>Retinue</hi> and Appurtenances, could be propagated, <hi>ex traduce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Korah,</hi> that great Rebel, was a <hi>Prieſt</hi> too, one of the Sons of <hi>Lew,</hi> and one of the <hi>Princes</hi> of the Aſſembly (as <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.2.) and of all theſe 250 Princes, mentioned <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.2. Men of <hi>renown,</hi> famous in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> he was the <hi>chief;</hi> (for according to the cuſtom of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> from whence they came, their <hi>Princes</hi> were <hi>Prieſts,)</hi> yet that would not <hi>ſerve,</hi> he will be <hi>Chief-Priest</hi> or nothing, <hi>aut</hi> Caeſar <hi>aut nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106837:15"/>as <hi>Moſes</hi> Articles againſt him, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. of the 16th of <hi>Numb.</hi> and to <hi>compaſs</hi> his deſign, he turns <hi>Independant</hi> Miniſter, and <hi>ſides</hi> with the People, that, by theſe <hi>Rounds</hi> of the Ladder, he might <hi>climb</hi> up to his deſired <hi>Height.</hi> Ambition has no <hi>Reins,</hi> never knows to make a <hi>ſtop,</hi> is always the <hi>Father</hi> of Rebellion, though <hi>Religion</hi> may be the <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father,</hi> and give it a <hi>Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Was not <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> Man amongſt the <hi>new</hi> Common-wealths men that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet that's not <hi>enough;</hi> but he <hi>Bandyes</hi> with his <hi>holy</hi> Siſter <hi>Miriam</hi> the <hi>Propheteſs</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> to get the <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> Numb. 12.1. and to effect this, firſt they <hi>rip</hi> up a <hi>Fault</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 40 Years, (contrary to the Law againſt ſtrange Wives) in the <hi>Marriage</hi> of a poor <hi>Black-moor</hi> Woman, called there an <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Woman; the <hi>true</hi> cauſe of their diſcontent breaks forth, <hi>Hath the Lord indeed only ſpoken by Moſes, and hath he not alſo ſpoken by us!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that it is <hi>certain</hi> as well as an <hi>old</hi> Rule, that he that goes about to <hi>ſpy</hi> faults in his Superiors, and <hi>blaze</hi> them in <hi>publick</hi> to their ſhame, that Man certainly is going about to <hi>rebell,</hi> and pick a <hi>quarrel</hi> with them: Firſt he renders them <hi>dirty,</hi> and then they are fit for nothing but to be <hi>rubb'd;</hi> firſt array them in <hi>Bear-skins,</hi> then ſets <hi>Dogs</hi> upon them to <hi>worry</hi> them.</p>
               <p>There's a <hi>Writ</hi> in Law called <hi>Ne injuſte vexes,</hi> vex not any Man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly; and the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>old</hi> were forbidden to <hi>vex</hi> a Stranger; but for a <hi>King</hi> to be <hi>Vexed,</hi> Oppreſſed, and at laſt <hi>Murdered</hi> by his own <hi>Subjects,</hi> as <hi>Barbarouſly,</hi> as <hi>Bloodily,</hi> in the midſt of his Kingdoms, and in the Strength of his Years, his Friends and loving Subjects being helpleſs <hi>Spectators,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Caitiffs</hi> reviled him, and <hi>triumphed</hi> in their unparallell'd <hi>Maſſacre</hi> at his <hi>own</hi> Gates, is a piece of <hi>horrid</hi> Butchery, as <hi>matchleſs</hi> as <hi>odious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all this with the <hi>applauſe</hi> of Juſtice and Devotion!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herod,</hi> who at one <hi>Draught quaff'd</hi> the blood of 14000 Infant-<hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemites,</hi> and his own <hi>Sons</hi> among the reſt, leſt the bloody cup ſhould not be a <hi>brim-full</hi> potion of Horror; <hi>Tyberius, Nero, Caligula, Otho</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Julian, Commodus</hi> (cunctis Incommodus) <hi>Domitian Diocleſian, Charles</hi> the 9th of <hi>France</hi> and all thoſe <hi>Monſters</hi> of Men that ever liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, might here (dull <hi>Truants</hi> in murdering <hi>Proficienties</hi>) have gone to <hi>School,</hi> and learnt new <hi>Lectures</hi> of Cruelty and Barbariſm.</p>
               <p>'Twas an <hi>Inhumane</hi> ſpeech of <hi>Hannibal</hi> (if true what's <hi>ſtoried</hi> of him) that no <hi>Proſpect</hi> did ever ſo much <hi>delight</hi> him, as a <hi>Ditch</hi> (which he once ſaw) running over with <hi>Man</hi>'s blood; But it is too true, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106837:15"/>no <hi>Sight</hi> could pleaſe ſome Wretches but that of the effuſion of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> Man's Blood, yea an Innocent <hi>King</hi>'s Blood? as if they did make choice of their <hi>Bits</hi> in their cruel <hi>Boulimy</hi>'s; The Blood of <hi>Goats</hi> will ſoften <hi>Adamants,</hi> but the <hi>precious</hi> Royal blood did not, has not, and (I fear) does not yet (Oh <hi>unhallowed</hi> Saints!) <hi>moliſy</hi> your more <hi>Adamantine</hi> Hearts, and <hi>ſeared</hi> Conſciences: 'Tis Juſt, with God to give you <hi>blood</hi> to drink for you are <hi>worthy; Satia te ſanguine quem ſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> would be <hi>but</hi> a due <hi>Retaliation;</hi> to uſe <hi>David</hi>'s words, <hi>Scatter thou the People that delight in War.</hi> What! Is not your <hi>inſatiable</hi> Thirſts yet ſatisfied? but as if the Sins that you have done, were not <hi>Scarlet</hi> enough, do you yet endeavour, by more <hi>blood,</hi> to <hi>crimſon</hi> them to a deeper <hi>dye</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing would ſatisfie <hi>Fareſius</hi> (the Pope's Champion) but to <hi>ride</hi> his Horſe up to the Saddle-<hi>skirts</hi> in the blood of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and do you cry down the <hi>Pope,</hi> and yet <hi>avouch</hi> the cruelty of the worſt of <hi>Popes</hi> by more diſmal <hi>Paralells?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do you make a <hi>Jest</hi> at Murder, as that <hi>Queen</hi> Mother of <hi>France,</hi> who viewing the fatal <hi>Landskip</hi> of the dead <hi>Carcaſes</hi> of her Proteſtant Subjects, <hi>ſmiled</hi> and ſaid, It was the handſomeſt <hi>Piece</hi> of <hi>Tapiſtry</hi> ſhe ever beheld? 'Tis a <hi>ſad</hi> Conſcience that can Joy at the thoughts of this days Mournful Remembrance otherwiſe than from the ſenſe of Godly Sorrow at this days Sad Remembrance; no good Man can Repent ſuch a Repentance.</p>
               <p>Have you no way to be Villanous enough, except ye call Heaven to Witneſs and aſſiſt at ſuch Unheard of Villanies? Ye Sons of <hi>Cain!</hi> muſt ye yet kill your <hi>Brethren,</hi> and that for Devotion-ſake?</p>
               <p>Or, with wicked <hi>Herod,</hi> Pretend to Worſhip, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.8. when ye Intend to Murder him? <hi>Cur bonificas?</hi> why Trimmeſt thou thy way to ſeck Love, and why doſt thou yet Teach the wicked ones thy Ways? Are you afraid that Dull Poſterity ſhould turn <hi>Truants</hi> to your <hi>skillful</hi> Maſſacres; and not get your bloody <hi>Manuſcripts</hi> by <hi>Heart,</hi> that you, even yet (under the <hi>notion</hi> of <hi>Purity) teach</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> ones and the <hi>Innocent</hi> ones your ways? when for all your Goſpel-<hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> we know too well, ye intend to practice no <hi>ſaying</hi> in the Goſpel, but that in <hi>Mat,</hi> 21.38. <hi>This is the Heir, come let us kill him, and ſieze upon his Inheritance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How then canſt thou ſay, <hi>I am polluted?</hi> Behold thy way in the <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> (in the <hi>Golgotha</hi> to which theſe once flouriſhing <hi>Kingdoms</hi> have been reduced) Let this <hi>Day</hi> reprove thee, know what thou haſt done; For
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106837:16"/>in thy skirts is found the blood of the Souls of the poor Innocents, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.34. <hi>I have not ſound it upon ſecret ſearch but upon all theſe:</hi> yet thou ſayeſt, <hi>Becauſe I am Innocent</hi> — Behold the <hi>Revenger</hi> of the blood of his <hi>Martyrs</hi> will yet <hi>plead</hi> with thee, becauſe thou ſayeſt, <hi>I am Innocent, Jer.</hi> 2.35. Nothing but <hi>Death</hi> could, under the Law, <hi>expiate</hi> Sins committed preſumptuouſly, [<hi>Hebrew</hi>] <hi>With a High hand,</hi> Numb. 15.30. Such as was this <hi>Concatenation</hi> of Villanies, that fought neither with <hi>ſmall</hi> nor <hi>great,</hi> but only with the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael: — Hunc ipſum Petimus,</hi> as that <hi>Ruſſian</hi> cryed who flew the <hi>great Guſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavus Adolphus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, <hi>Reſtore,</hi> Reſtore your <hi>forfeited</hi> Loyalty: Talk not of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Church and State, till you have firſt reformed your <hi>own</hi> diſobedient and <hi>ſtubborn</hi> hearts; <hi>firſt</hi> waſh your bloody hands, and <hi>gargle</hi> your ſlanderous Throats, and then you need not <hi>bluſh</hi> when you ſpeak of <hi>Reformation;</hi> 'till this be <hi>done,</hi> He is unpardonably <hi>credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> that will lend an <hi>Ear</hi> to your <hi>noiſe</hi> of <hi>the Goſpel, the Goſpel!</hi> Good Hearts! It were very <hi>pretty</hi> if it were not <hi>painted,</hi> but in <hi>earneſt</hi> we may ſay by <hi>woful</hi> experience of your <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as <hi>Saluſt</hi> ſays of <hi>Amelia,</hi> Amelia <hi>Oreſtilla, Praeter formam nihil unquam bonus laudavit;</hi> There's nothing <hi>skin-deep</hi> praiſe-worthy in it; Bull-ruſh-like, or Sepulchre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or a <hi>Roſe-tree</hi> in <hi>Autumn, — cecidit Roſa, manet Spina,</hi> when the <hi>flower</hi> is off, how <hi>pitifully</hi> it looks? <hi>Oh quantum haec Niobe!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, then every one that <hi>hears</hi> me this <hi>day</hi> upon this <hi>occaſion</hi> of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,</hi> (rehearſing to us that of <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.16. <hi>The Crown is fallen from our Heads, wo unto us that we have Sinned)</hi> lay your <hi>Hands</hi> upon your <hi>Hearts,</hi> and ſeriouſly <hi>empannel</hi> your Thoughts in this grand <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt;</hi> Have I ſo much as <hi>conſented</hi> to the ſhedding the Blood of this <hi>Innocent</hi> Martyr; or have I in any-wiſe approved of it, or juſtified thoſe that did it ſince, tho' perhaps then unborn? The very <hi>conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of a Cheat was miraculouſly puniſhed with <hi>Death,</hi> Act. 5.10. and yet the Text does not ſay that <hi>Sapphira conſented</hi> to it, but only was <hi>Privy</hi> to it, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. and did not do her beſt to prevent It; ſure I am then, this bloody <hi>Butchery</hi> muſt, upon this Account, be <hi>filed</hi> up for a <hi>National</hi> Sin, as God has in Juſtice <hi>ſcored</hi> upon us, for this Blood, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny National <hi>Plagues,</hi> And (if that be Scripture in <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.21.) God will yet <hi>appear,</hi> rendring Vengeance to all ſuch who have not <hi>repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Murthers, nor</hi> of their <hi>Sorceries,</hi> nor of their <hi>Fornications,</hi> nor of their <hi>Thefts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106837:16"/>
               <p> Oh, that you that hear me this Day, may be (as the Poſts of the Doors were by the Blood of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> in that day of Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) ſo Waſhed (by unfeigned Contrition) in the Blood of the Lamb, that when the deſtroying Angel ſhall yet make Inquiſition for this Royal Blood, he may paſs over us!</p>
               <p>Talk not of Religion 'till this be Done; Pray no more 'till this be done; bring no more vain Oblations 'till this be done: <hi>For, when ye ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you, ſaith the Lord; yea, when ye make many prayers, I will not hear, your hands are full of blood,</hi> Iſa. 1.13, 15. <hi>But, deliver us from Blood-guiltineſs, O God thou God of our Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
